<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<base xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" type="string">
 <strings>
  <!--input/spkingdoms/spkingdoms_aquitaine.xml-->
  <string id="aquitaine_kingdom_name" text="Duchy of Aquitaine"/>
  <string id="aquitaine_kingdom_short_name" text="Aquitaine"/>
  <string id="aquitaine_kingdom_title" text="Duchy of Aquitaine"/>
  <string id="aquitaine_ruler_title" text="Duke"/>
  <string id="aquitaine_kingdom_text" text="The Duchy of Aquitaine emerged in the 7th–8th centuries as one of the largest and most influential feudal realms in southwestern France. Its identity grew from the legacy of the former Roman province and the traditions of the Visigothic Kingdom. By the 9th and 10th centuries, the counts of Poitiers had established themselves as the ruling dynasty, gradually unifying the region under their authority. By the year 1100, Aquitaine functioned as a largely autonomous state. The dukes commanded their own armies, minted their own coinage, and arranged political marriages without permission from the French crown. Ambitious and powerful, they tried to extend their influence into neighboring territories such as Gascony and Auvergne, often competing directly with the Counts of Toulouse for dominance in the south. Aquitaine’s independence began to erode after the marriage of Eleanor of Aquitaine—one of the most influential women of the Middle Ages—to King Louis VII of France in 1137, and later to Henry II of England in 1152. These unions tied the duchy to larger political powers and gradually reduced its autonomy. The final loss of independence came in 1453, at the close of the Hundred Years’ War, when Aquitaine was absorbed into the royal domain of France."/>
  <!--input/spkingdoms/spkingdoms_bavaria.xml-->
  <string id="bavaria_kingdom_name" text="Duchy of Bavaria"/>
  <string id="bavaria_kingdom_short_name" text="Bavaria"/>
  <string id="bavaria_kingdom_title" text="Duchy of Bavaria"/>
  <string id="bavaria_ruler_title" text="Duke"/>
  <string id="bavaria_kingdom_text" text="Between 1050 and 1150, Bavaria was one of the largest and most influential duchies of the Holy Roman Empire. Although it was formally subordinate to the emperor, in practice it operated with independence. The Welf dukes worked to strengthen their regional authority and frequently clashed with the imperial government, especially during the Investiture Controversy and disputes over control of church offices. In 1077, Duke Welf I backed the anti‑king Rudolf of Swabia against Emperor Henry IV. As punishment, he was deprived of the Bavarian duchy—an event that vividly illustrated the ongoing tension between Bavaria and the imperial center. Bavaria’s foreign policy was active and ambitious. The duchy took part in the Crusades, forged alliances with neighboring principalities, and competed for influence in Italy and the Eastern March. The Bavarian rulers also sought to expand their territories through strategic marriages and control of key trade routes. These long‑term ambitions eventually paved the way for the rise of the Wittelsbach dynasty, which would soon become the dominant power in the region."/>
  <!--input/spkingdoms/spkingdoms_bohemia.xml-->
  <string id="bohemia_kingdom_name" text="Duchy of Bohemia"/>
  <string id="bohemia_kingdom_short_name" text="Bohemia"/>
  <string id="bohemia_kingdom_title" text="Duchy of Bohemia"/>
  <string id="bohemia_ruler_title" text="Duke"/>
  <string id="bohemia_kingdom_text" text="In 1100, Bohemia was still a duchy within the Holy Roman Empire and had not yet gained the official status of a kingdom. Although Duke Vladislav II had received a non‑hereditary royal title from Emperor Henry IV in 1085, this was largely a political gesture rather than true recognition of a sovereign monarchy. Inside the duchy, tensions grew between the ruling Přemyslid family and rival noble clans—most notably the powerful Vršovci, who were violently eliminated in 1108. Despite its formal dependence on the empire, Bohemia maintained a significant degree of autonomy and played an active role in regional politics, competing for influence in Moravia and Silesia. Later, in 1198, Prince Přemysl Otakar I secured recognition of a hereditary royal title, marking the true beginning of the Kingdom of Bohemia."/>
  <!--input/spkingdoms/spkingdoms_bretagne.xml-->
  <string id="bretagne_kingdom_name" text="Duchy of Bretagne"/>
  <string id="bretagne_kingdom_short_name" text="Bretagne"/>
  <string id="bretagne_kingdom_title" text="Duchy of Bretagne"/>
  <string id="bretagne_ruler_title" text="Duke"/>
  <string id="bretagne_kingdom_text" text="In 1100, the Duchy of Bretagne was ruled by Alan IV de Cornouaille of the House of Cornouaille. Although formally a vassal of the French king, the duchy in practice operated as an almost independent feudal state. Breton nobles played an active role in the Norman conquest of England—especially members of the House of Penthièvre, such as Brian de Bretagne, who received English lands from William the Conqueror. Alan IV further strengthened ties with the Norman dynasty by marrying Constance de Normandie, William’s daughter, creating a political alliance that linked Bretagne closely to both Normandy and England. In its foreign policy, the duchy sought to balance the competing influences of Anjou, Normandy, and France through participation in the Crusades and carefully arranged dynastic marriages. Despite growing pressure from the French crown, Bretagne preserved its own political institutions, language, and cultural identity. The Breton language and the ermine coat of arms—later a defining symbol of the region—remained central to its distinct character."/>
  <!--input/spkingdoms/spkingdoms_croatia.xml-->
  <string id="croatia_kingdom_name" text="Kingdom of Croatia"/>
  <string id="croatia_kingdom_short_name" text="Croatia"/>
  <string id="croatia_kingdom_title" text="Kingdom of Croatia"/>
  <string id="croatia_ruler_title" text="King"/>
  <string id="croatia_kingdom_text" text="In the 11th century, the Croatian Kingdom was ruled by the Trpimirović dynasty, first under King Stephen I and later under his successor, Dmitar Zvonimir. Their domestic policy focused on strengthening royal authority, developing a feudal system, and supporting the Catholic Church, often in close cooperation with the papacy. In foreign affairs, Croatia carefully balanced between the influence of Byzantium and the Holy Roman Empire, while also maintaining ties with Hungary through dynastic marriages. After Zvonimir’s death in 1089, a succession crisis erupted, creating instability that allowed the Hungarian king Coloman to intervene. The final ruler of an independent Croatia, Petar Snačić, was killed in 1097 at the Battle of Mount Gvozd while resisting the Hungarian advance. In 1102, Croatia entered a personal union with Hungary, bringing an end to its political independence."/>
  <!--input/spkingdoms/spkingdoms_france.xml-->
  <string id="france_new_kingdom_name" text="Crown of France"/>
  <string id="france_new_kingdom_short_name" text="France"/>
  <string id="france_new_kingdom_title" text="Crown of France"/>
  <string id="france_new_ruler_title" text="King"/>
  <string id="france_new_kingdom_text" text="France emerged as a unified kingdom in the late 10th century, when Hugh Capet was elected king in 987 and founded the Capetian dynasty. By 1100, however, royal authority remained limited: the king directly controlled only the lands around Paris and Orléans, while powerful feudal houses - Blois, Anjou, Normandy, and Flanders - governed their territories with near-complete independence. The monarchy was weak, and the king relied heavily on alliances with loyal vassals to counter the influence of Normandy and the growing power of England. In the 14th and 15th centuries, France was shaken by the Hundred Years’ War, a long and destructive conflict with England. The eventual French victory in 1453 strengthened the crown and marked the beginning of a gradual process of political centralization. Over the following centuries, France experienced the rise of absolute monarchy, the upheavals of the 1789 Revolution, and ultimately its transformation into a modern republic."/>
  <!--input/spkingdoms/spkingdoms_germany.xml-->
  <string id="hre_kingdom_name" text="Crown of Holy Roman Empire"/>
  <string id="hre_kingdom_short_name" text="Holy Roman"/>
  <string id="hre_kingdom_title" text="Crown of Holy Roman Empire"/>
  <string id="hre_ruler_title" text="Emperor"/>
  <string id="hre_kingdom_text" text="The Holy Roman Empire was a vast, decentralized federation made up of duchies, bishoprics, and self-governing cities, each with its own traditions and degree of autonomy. It emerged in 962, when Otto I was crowned emperor and sought to revive the legacy of the Western Roman Empire. Although the emperor was considered the supreme authority, his real power was constrained by influential regional rulers. Electors, princes, and other high-ranking vassals often pursued their own interests and could openly resist imperial directives.The empire ultimately came to an end in 1806, when Emperor Francis II abdicated under pressure from Napoleon. Yet despite its political fragmentation, the Holy Roman Empire remained a key force in shaping the political landscape, legal traditions, and cultural development of medieval and early modern Europe."/>
  <!--input/spkingdoms/spkingdoms_netherlands.xml-->
  <string id="netherlands_kingdom_name" text="Netherlands"/>
  <string id="netherlands_kingdom_short_name" text="Netherlands"/>
  <string id="netherlands_kingdom_title" text="Netherlands"/>
  <string id="netherlands_ruler_title" text="Duke"/>
  <string id="netherlands_kingdom_text" text="The Low Countries, or the Netherlands, was the name for a historical region that included the lands of modern Belgium, the Netherlands, Luxembourg, and parts of northern France and northern Germany. Around 1100, this area was divided into many small states—some under the Holy Roman Empire, others under France—yet most of them enjoyed significant autonomy. During this period, the House of Leuven built a wide network of dynastic and political alliances, managing to bring much of the region under its influence. Although this did not result in the formation of a unified state, the foundations for future consolidation were already visible. Standing apart from the rest was Frisian Freedom, a unique community that rejected feudal structures and maintained its own traditions of self‑governance."/>
  <!--input/spkingdoms/spkingdoms_pisa.xml-->
  <string id="pisa_kingdom_name" text="Republic of Pisa"/>
  <string id="pisa_kingdom_short_name" text="Pisa"/>
  <string id="pisa_kingdom_title" text="Republic of Pisa"/>
  <string id="pisa_ruler_title" text="Consul"/>
  <string id="pisa_kingdom_text" text="Between the 11th and 13th centuries, the Republic of Pisa evolved from a provincial Tuscan city into one of the major maritime powers of the Mediterranean. In the 11th century, it effectively freed itself from the authority of the Margraviate of Tuscany and began building a formidable fleet, taking part in crusades, naval campaigns, and long‑distance trade. By the 12th century, Pisan ships dominated key sea routes, and the republic’s influence stretched across Sardinia, Corsica, and even the Balearic Islands. In 1114, Pisa launched a major naval expedition against Muslim pirates in Majorca, acting in alliance with Catalan forces. The 13th century marked the peak of Pisan power, when the republic stood as a rival to Genoa and Venice. However, the crushing defeat at the Battle of Meloria in 1284 signaled the beginning of Pisa’s decline."/>
  <!--input/spkingdoms/spkingdoms_pomerania.xml-->
  <string id="pomerania_kingdom_name" text="Duchy of Pomerania"/>
  <string id="pomerania_kingdom_short_name" text="Pomerania"/>
  <string id="pomerania_kingdom_title" text="Duchy of Pomerania"/>
  <string id="pomerania_ruler_title" text="Duke"/>
  <string id="pomerania_kingdom_text" text="Pomerania is a historical region along the southern coast of the Baltic Sea. Since ancient times, it was inhabited by the Pomeranians, an early West Slavic people. From the 10th century onward, the region became the target of competing powers. Poland sought to bring Pomerania under its control, while the Holy Roman Empire also aimed to extend its influence there. The local ruling dynasty, the Griffins, tried to preserve their autonomy by carefully balancing between these rival forces. Denmark, too, made repeated attempts to dominate the region. In 1116, Poland seized the western part of Pomerania and consolidated its authority through the Samborid dynasty. This area became known as Pomerelia. The remaining lands retained the name Pomerania, where the Griffins continued to rule for many generations as largely autonomous vassals of the Holy Roman Empire."/>
  <!--input/spkingdoms/spkingdoms_portugal.xml-->
  <string id="portugal_kingdom_name" text="County of Portugal"/>
  <string id="portugal_kingdom_short_name" text="Portugal"/>
  <string id="portugal_kingdom_title" text="County of Portugal"/>
  <string id="portugal_ruler_title" text="Count"/>
  <string id="portugal_kingdom_text" text="By 1100, the County of Portugal was ruled by Henry of Burgundy, who had married Teresa of León in 1093 and received the county as part of her dowry from her father, Alfonso VI of León. At this time, the territory was still in the process of consolidation, formed largely from lands recently reconquered from Muslim rule. Henry focused on strengthening local defenses and successfully repelled several Moorish incursions, helping to stabilize the frontier. The region was shaped by a distinctive Galician-Portuguese culture that emerged from the blending of Romanized Hispano-Romans, Suebi settlers, and newer Burgundian and Frankish influences brought by the ruling dynasty. Despite the presence of a foreign count, real power was shared with local noble families, many of whom traced their lineage back to Visigothic aristocracy and early leaders of the Christian Reconquista. These nobles enjoyed considerable autonomy while formally acknowledging Burgundian authority. Over time, these families became the foundation of an increasingly distinct political and social identity. Their cooperation—and occasional rivalry—with the Burgundian rulers would later play a decisive role in the emergence of an independent Kingdom of Portugal."/>
  <!--input/spkingdoms/spkingdoms_saxony.xml-->
  <string id="saxony_kingdom_name" text="Duchy of Saxony"/>
  <string id="saxony_kingdom_short_name" text="Saxony"/>
  <string id="saxony_kingdom_title" text="Duchy of Saxony"/>
  <string id="saxony_ruler_title" text="Duke"/>
  <string id="saxony_kingdom_text" text="In the 12th century, Saxony was one of the most powerful and influential duchies within the Holy Roman Empire. A few decades earlier, between 1073 and 1075, the region had risen in open rebellion against Emperor Henry IV, driven by his attempts to centralize authority and by the heavy exploitation of Saxon lands. The conflict left deep scars and shaped Saxony’s political landscape for generations. Around 1100, the duchy was ruled by Magnus Billung, the last male heir of the long‑standing Billung dynasty. His death in 1106 ended the family’s rule and opened the way for a new political order. Power passed to Lothar von Supplinburg, a skilled and ambitious nobleman who would later ascend to the imperial throne as Holy Roman Emperor. His rise strengthened Saxony’s prestige but also intensified rivalries among the local nobility, as various families competed for influence under the new regime. These internal tensions, combined with the growing ambitions of neighboring principalities, gradually weakened the unity of the duchy. Over time, Saxony began to fragment into smaller territorial lordships, a process that would continue throughout the 12th and 13th centuries and eventually reshape the political map of northern Germany."/>
  <!--input/spkingdoms/spkingdoms_swabia.xml-->
  <string id="swabia_kingdom_name" text="Duchy of Swabia"/>
  <string id="swabia_kingdom_short_name" text="Swabia"/>
  <string id="swabia_kingdom_title" text="Duchy of Swabia"/>
  <string id="swabia_ruler_title" text="Duke"/>
  <string id="swabia_kingdom_text" text="In 1100, the Duchy of Swabia was ruled by Frederick I of Hohenstaufen, appointed duke by Emperor Henry IV in 1079. The Hohenstaufen line was founded by Count Frederick (d. 1105), who built Staufen Castle in the Swabian Jura and earned the emperor’s trust through steadfast loyalty. As a reward, he received the ducal title and strengthened his position further by marrying Henry IV’s daughter, Agnes. Swabia was one of the five great stem duchies of the Holy Roman Empire, and its dukes ranked among the most influential nobles in Germany. At the time, two major noble houses were still competing for dominance in the region, but the Hohenstaufen gradually emerged as the leading force. The Swabian aristocracy had a long tradition of supporting the Saxon kings and later the Salian emperors, especially during the Investiture Controversy, which shaped imperial politics for decades."/>
  <!--input/spkingdoms/spkingdoms_toulouse.xml-->
  <string id="toulouse_kingdom_name" text="County of Toulouse"/>
  <string id="toulouse_kingdom_short_name" text="Toulouse"/>
  <string id="toulouse_kingdom_title" text="County of Toulouse"/>
  <string id="toulouse_ruler_title" text="Count"/>
  <string id="toulouse_kingdom_text" text="The County of Toulouse was one of the most powerful and autonomous principalities in southern France during the Middle Ages. It emerged in 778, when Charlemagne established it as a frontier region to defend the empire from Muslim incursions coming from the Iberian Peninsula. By the late 9th century, Toulouse had effectively slipped out of royal control, and its counts ruled almost as independent princes over extensive lands that included Quercy, Albi, and parts of Provence.Around 1100, Count Raymond IV was a leading figure of the First Crusade and played a key role in the creation of the County of Tripoli in the Levant, reflecting Toulouse’s far‑reaching ambitions and active involvement in Mediterranean politics. Despite this strength, the county’s autonomy began to weaken during the Albigensian Crusade (1209–1229), when French royal forces intervened to suppress the Cathar movement and extend royal authority into the south. Toulouse never fully recovered its former independence. In 1271, after the death of Count Alphonse without an heir, the county was formally absorbed into the royal domain of France."/>
  <!--input/spkingdoms/spkingdoms_wales.xml-->
  <string id="wales_kingdom_name" text="Kingdoms of Wales"/>
  <string id="wales_kingdom_short_name" text="Wales"/>
  <string id="wales_kingdom_title" text="Kingdoms of Wales"/>
  <string id="wales_ruler_title" text="King"/>
  <string id="wales_kingdom_text" text="By 1100, most of the southern Welsh kingdoms - such as Morgannwg, Gwent, and Brycheiniog - had already fallen under Norman control and were incorporated into the border zone known as the Welsh March. Norman lords established castles and lordships there, securing their dominance over the lowlands and river valleys. In contrast, the kingdoms of Gwynedd, Powys, and parts of Deheubarth managed to preserve a degree of independence. This was especially true in the rugged, mountainous regions collectively known as Pura Wallia, where difficult terrain limited Norman military effectiveness and helped local rulers maintain control. The balance of power shifted sharply after the death of Rhys ap Tewdwr in 1093. His kingdom of Deheubarth briefly collapsed, and much of its territory was divided among Norman barons. Nevertheless, Welsh princes did not abandon resistance. They relied on their knowledge of the landscape, mobile warfare, and, at times, support from Irish allies to challenge Norman authority. In 1094, a major uprising erupted across much of Wales. Although it was eventually suppressed, it marked the beginning of a long cycle of revolts that would continue into the 13th century. These struggles periodically restored Welsh rule in significant areas, most notably under Gruffudd ap Cynan and his son Owain Gwynedd in the north, and later under Rhys ap Gruffudd in the south during the 12th century."/>
  <!--input/spkingdoms/spkingdoms_wends.xml-->
  <string id="wends_kingdom_name" text="States of Wends"/>
  <string id="wends_kingdom_short_name" text="Wends"/>
  <string id="wends_kingdom_title" text="States of Wends"/>
  <string id="wends_ruler_title" text="Duke"/>
  <string id="wends_kingdom_text" text="The term Wends was used by German‑speaking peoples to describe various Slavic tribes living along the Baltic Sea coast between the Elbe and Oder rivers. Both Germany and Denmark exerted strong political and cultural pressure on these communities. In the mid‑11th century, Duke Gottschalk attempted to impose Christianity across the region, but his reforms provoked a major pagan uprising in 1066, led by the chieftain Kruto. Gottschalk was killed, and Kruto, supported by the pagan nobility, seized power. As prince, Kruto launched frequent raids into Saxon territory, including the destruction of Hamburg in 1072, and maintained control until 1093, when he was overthrown and killed by Gottschalk’s son, Heinrich, who returned with Danish backing. These turbulent events ushered in a period of relative independence for the Wendish lands. Instead of forming a unified state, the region fragmented into several Slavic duchies, which often fought among themselves and struggled to establish lasting cohesion."/>
 </strings>
</base>
